<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A word from the north, sounded into the south, heard, and received of many. Jesus Christ the Son of God, which is the true light which lighteth every man that cometh into the world; and all that receive this light, and believe in this light, and are obedient to this light, they receive power and do become the sons of God. And as I have heard, so I have and do see in the true light, and am bold to give forth my testimonie that it is true, and there is no other way to salvation but by it. And therefore do I warn all people, and thee, O Kent, with the citie of Canterbury, and town of Maidstone, and all thy magistrates in you all, betimes to consider and take heed that none of you be anie longer enemies to it and its ministers, lest you be found fighters against God. Thomas Howsegoe.</title>
            <author>Howsegoe, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86656</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3197</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E923_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207540</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866584</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866584</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168482</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86656)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168482)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 139:E923[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A word from the north, sounded into the south, heard, and received of many. Jesus Christ the Son of God, which is the true light which lighteth every man that cometh into the world; and all that receive this light, and believe in this light, and are obedient to this light, they receive power and do become the sons of God. And as I have heard, so I have and do see in the true light, and am bold to give forth my testimonie that it is true, and there is no other way to salvation but by it. And therefore do I warn all people, and thee, O Kent, with the citie of Canterbury, and town of Maidstone, and all thy magistrates in you all, betimes to consider and take heed that none of you be anie longer enemies to it and its ministers, lest you be found fighters against God. Thomas Howsegoe.</title>
                  <author>Howsegoe, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Giles Calvert, at the black Spread-Eagle neer the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 15"; in Howseyor "g" written over the y and "e" written over the r.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Kent (England) --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168482:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A WORD From the NORTH, Sounded into the SOUTH, Heard, and received of Many.</p>
            <p>Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God, which is the true light which lighteth every man that cometh into the world; and all that receive this light, and believe in this light, and are obedient to this light, they receive power and do become the ſons of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as I have heard, ſo I have and do ſee in the true light, and am bold to give forth my teſtimonie that it is true, and there is no other way to ſalvation but by it.</p>
            <p>And therefore do I warn all the people, and thee, O Kent, with the citie of Canterbury, and town of Maidſtone, and all thy Magiſtrates in you all, betimes to conſider and take heed that none of you be anie longer enemies to it and its Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, leſt you be found fighters againſt God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Howſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the black Spread-Eagle neer the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:168482:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168482:2"/>
            <head>A Warning unto all people that live wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonly upon the Earth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>O, wo, ſaith the Lord to the Inhabitants of the Earth, that live wantonly and proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the earth, which oppreſſeth the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, and murders the juſt; that ſay, Who is the Lord? and to the Almighty, Depart, we deſire not the knowledge of thy wayes; we wil not have this man Chriſt, the light which enlightneth every man that cometh into the world, to reign over us, to rule in us, to be the only true Teacher unto us, by him to be governed and convinced of all ſin, and to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved for all our evil deeds of darkneſs; for if him we receive, then all our gain of unrighteouſneſs will be loſt; all our pomp and glories of this world muſt be denyed; all our evil vain thoughts; all our formal Profeſſion without the life, out of the poſſeſſion, by this light wil be condemned; and all our forms without the power, by it, and by the children of it are denyed; and if this be received, all ſin and iniquity muſt be denied while we are here in this life.</p>
            <p>And we have been taught by our Teachers and Prieſts, That while we are here we cannot be freed from ſin; and that none can be without ſin while they are in this life; and that freedom from our ſins ſhould be in another world; and them we have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, and this for truth we have received. And for the light of Chriſt that ſhews ſin and leads out of ſin, which was in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168482:3"/>
we confeſs Scriptures ſpeaks of ſuch a thing, and there is ſomething in our conſciences tells us it is truth; we ſhould not ſerve ſin and the Devil here in this life; and we are condemned often by it when we do evil, though no eye of man ſees us; and this is the Witneſs of God in our conſciences, and the Witneſs is true, but it's a croſs to our Wills and Luſts. And our Prieſts and learned men they muſt needs know, and they have taught us otherwiſe, That we cannot be free here; and we ſee they are as we, and do the ſame things that we do, and we hope we ſhall do as well as they. And further, we ſee that the Rulers and great ones but very few of them receive this Teſtimony, nor own this Light of Chriſt to be ruled by it; and if we receive it, and be ordered by it, then we muſt deny all ungodlineſs and vvordly luſts, all our pride and oppreſſion, all our vain words, and light idle communication, jeſting and fooliſh talking, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and double-dealing. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is a great croſs to our own wills, and we ſhall be a croſs to the will of man, and the povvers of the Earth, and the Prieſts of the Nation vvill frown upon us. Yea, further, it tells us, we may not think our own thoughts, nor ſpeak our own words; but a watch muſt be kept over all. And that tells us, if we commit ſin we are of the Devil; and that him to whom we yeild obedience, his ſervants we are; and that the Tree is known by its fruit; and that no unclean thing can enter into the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God: and that if we be Chriſts, we muſt be new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and that his blood cleanſeth from all ſin, we acknowledge this to be truth: But we have received another teſtimony of men, and moſt profeſſors and people are of this judgement, that is, We cannot be free from ſin here.</p>
            <p>And with the Enemy to their eternal peace here many joine, and deny the pure Light of Chriſt within them, and refuſeth its teachings and leadings out of all ungodlineſs and wordly luſts, to a holy and godly life and converſation in this preſent evil world, and to have no fellowſhip with the unfruitful works and workers of darkneſs, but to reprove them plainly: Here the vain world and carnal profeſſors joynes together, and both conclude that this they cannot be nor do, and ſo exclude them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from its leadings, which would make them to be found
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168482:3"/>
meet to be partakers of the Inheritance of the Saints in Light.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſay to the Almighty, Depart, depart, we deſire not the knowledge of thy Law; theſe deny the grace of God which bringeth ſalvation; theſe deny the living way to the Father; theſe deny the power of God; theſe reſiſt the Light in which the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is placed, and he that reſiſteth this Power, reſiſteth the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God: theſe deny the Lord that bought them, and ſuch ſhall bring damnation upon themſelves; for this is witneſſed and teſtified, that there is no other way to ſalvation then that which was from the beginning, Chriſt the true Light, which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightneth every one that cometh into the world, and was given for a light of the Gentiles, the ſalvation of God unto the ends of the world, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4.9.6. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.47. (Mark) <hi>He was given for a light,</hi> he was, he is the true light; <hi>he was given for a Covenant, Iſa.</hi> 42.6. All that have not him to be the true Light, have not the Covenant, are out of the Covenant, denies the door of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance to the Father; for none can come to the Father but by him.</p>
            <p>And ſo all people be warned what you do; for where this cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ground is ſtanding, and darkneſs over the face of the earth, and the light denyed, there the curſed fruit is brought forth as hatred, pride, envie; wrath, emulation, ſtrife, ſeditions, hypocriſie, hereſies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and all fruits of the fleſh have a habitation in that kingdom where <hi>Pharaoh</hi> rules, which oppreſſes the Iſrael of God; there <hi>Judas</hi> dwelleth that betrayes the juſt; there is that envious generation harboured that cryes, Deliver to us the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dererer, and crucifie the light, the Son of God.</p>
            <p>Therefore all people, I warn you all betimes, conſider what you do that deny the light of Chriſt, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y it to be ordered, and calls it natural; it matters not what you profeſs or talk of in words; all your Religion and Profeſſion is but vain, your vain words will not ſave you, no more then it did the generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which you may read of, who ſaid to Chriſt, we have eat and drunk in thy preſence, and preached of thee in the Streets, and in thy Name done great things, which went far; yet ſaid Chriſt to them, Depart ye workers of Iniquity, I never knew you, <hi>Matt.</hi> 7.22.23.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:168482:4"/>And here you are all that hate the light, and denyes the tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of it, and hates the Meſſengers and Meſſengers of it, who are ſent to you of the Lord to bear vvitneſs of the true Light vvhich enlightneth every man that cometh into the vvorld, to them many of you ſay, Depart out of our Coaſts, our Cities, and Towns, we deſire not the knowledge of this vvay; and ſome of them you ſtock, whip, and impriſon, by the which you are made manifeſt of what generation you are: And this I declare from the Lord unto you all whatever you be, high or low, rich or poor, vvho are Enemies in your minds to the light of Chriſt, and the vvitneſſes of it, and refuſe by it to be ordered in all your whole lives and converſations, to the glory of our God: There vvil a day come upon you in the which he ſhall ſay, Depart, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from me and mine, ye vvorkers of Iniquity, I knovv you not; and then a ſad lamentation of hovvling and bitterneſs wil be upon you, and vvo and miſery ſhall be your portion for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
            <p>Therefore novv vvhile you have time, prize it; now is the day of your viſitation, and many large declarations hath been of late ſent forth amongſt you in this Nation, by which you ſhall be left without excuſe, for his ſound is gone forth through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the earth, have ye not all heard? and have not many been convinced by the Light, and that your Teacher is nigh you, and the vvitneſs for God is within you, and by it you have been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten judged and condemned for your evil deeds and hard ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, done and ſpoken maliciouſly againſt the innocent ſervants of the Lord: But how few among you have received and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved the vvitneſſes for God, and have felt the ſtrong Arm of the Lord in power to pluck you as brands out of the Fire.</p>
            <p>Are ye not yet for the greateſt part both Prieſts, Profeſſors, &amp; people, under all your names and titles whatever called, oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and reſiſting the ſpirit of the living God when it moves in you, and ſtrives with you, or ſpeaks in any ſent of the Lord un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, for the eternal good of your poor ſouls, which is of more vvorth then all the vvorld, even as your fathers have done ſo do ye, and therein have declared your ſelves enemies to God and his Miniſters, and judged your ſelves unworthy of eternal life.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:168482:4"/>Oh Nation! oh people! repent, repent betimes, and break off from the evil of all your vvayes and doings, that have been acted againſt the Lord, his vvitneſs within you, and his ſervants ſent amongſt you, and if you will return, return indeed to the Lord, and forſake all thy abominations by which the ſeed of God hath long been oppreſſed, and groans and cryes for deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance from under <hi>Pharoahs</hi> cruel bondage, the cryes of the which ſeed the Lord hath heard, and hath brought forth at this day in thouſands of his tender Lambs, who are redeemed from off the earth, to praiſe and glorifie his holy Name for evermore, who ſtand living Witneſſes for the living God of power this day, in this and many other Nations, who have not loved their lives, but given them to death for the teſtimony of Jeſus, who hath purchaſed them to be to himſelf a peculiar people, out of Kindreds, Tongues and Nations.</p>
            <p>And many more hath our God, with his eternal Love, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon, and his living pure light ſhined into, who ſtand ſingle in their ſouls, and in the light of Chriſt do wait for the pure living manifeſtation of the whole counſel and revelation of the will of God in every thing what he vvil have them to do and ſuffer for his Names ſake, who through Grace received, do witneſs, and in the light of Chriſt do ſee, and teſtifie againſt the vvorld its vvickedneſs, its vvayes, vvords, vvorſhips, vvorks, cuſtoms, faſhions, and ungodly converſations, and abominable uncleanneſſes thereof, and dare not have any fellowſhip with the unfruitful vvorks or vvorkers of darkneſs, but as moved of the Lord are made to reprove them plainly: Praiſes, praiſes be to our God for evermore.</p>
            <p>And now all people in love to your ſouls, which is more vvorth then all the vvorld, do I ſpeak, and do you warn and beſeech, to come off and forſake all your falſe Teachers and Hirelings, who vvalk not in nor by the Light of Chriſt, but are in <hi>Cains</hi> way, and <hi>Korahs</hi> vvay, and <hi>Balaams</hi> vvay, who deny to be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and guided by the Light of Chriſt in their own particular, and are Enemies to thoſe that vvalk in it, that vvil not receive it themſelves, nor enter the Kingdom of Heaven themſelves, nor ſuffer others to enter.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:168482:5"/>I ſay once more, Come off, come away from off all thoſe hard Mountains of leanneſs, where no pure Waters are, and come down to the true teacher, Chriſt the Light, which is nigh you all, in you all, which if you hear &amp; obey, vvil lead you into the good Land, the fruitful Land, where freſh Springs are alwaies open, where no want or barrenneſs is; it is to him I exhort you all to come, which will tell you truly all that ever you have done, that ever you have been, and let you ſee your ſecret ſins, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince you of them, and bring you to condemnation for them, and purifie and cleanſe you from them; and to all you that abide in him, and look for him, he ſhall appear the ſecond time with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin, unto ſalvation: But for all you who will not own him here before men, he ſhall you deny before his Father, which is in Heaven: And ſo while you have time priſe it, before that hour come upon you, in which time ſhall be no more, and then repentance ſhall be hid from your eyes, and the day of your vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation be over-paſt: Now is your day, priſe it, and receive the counſel of your friend, called</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:168482:5"/>
            <head>Oh County! Oh People! hear counſel in time.</head>
            <p>O <hi>Kent! Kent!</hi> hear the Word of the Lord unto thee: Thou art full, thou art full; thou art increaſed in Goods; thou art waxed wanton before me, ſaith the Lord: thou haſt kicked with the heel; thou haſt given me the back, but the face thou haſt turned away: thy iniquities are many; the ſins of <hi>Sod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m</hi> are found in thee, pride, idleneſs, and fulneſs of bread; but the cry of the needy in thee is not heard; thou haſt broken the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants and ſolemn Promiſes made unto me in the day of thy calamity and ſore troubles, when the Sword was within thy borders, and Wars within thy Gates. Thou waſt leſs indeed in the fire, in the fornace, then many other Shires and Counties; not ſo much blood was ſhed in thee; not ſo much plunder and burnings done in thee; but thou haſt forgotten the hand by which thou waſt ſmitten, and haſt not minded him whoſe Arm was ſtretched over thee to ſave, even me ſaith the Lord thou haſt forgotten and forſaken, who delivered thee for my own Names ſake, who hath now given thee peace, and ſent thee plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in thy dwellings; and thou haſt taken my Corn and my Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel in exceſs to gluttony; my Wine and my Drink to drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; my Wool and my Flax to ſatisfie thy luſts, thy pride and laſciviouſneſs, worſe then the Heathen; &amp; herein thou haſt ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceeded many other Counties and Shires, even as thou haſt excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them in my mercies: And theſe are thy Fruits, with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther abominations committed in thee O <hi>Kent,</hi> and yet thou draweſt near to me with thy lips, as a people uſe to do, and thou haſt gotten many in thee that make a profeſſion, and talk of me in words, ſaith the Lord, and they have gotten them ſeveral forms and likeneſs of me, and my worſhip, and my truth, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as they imagine in their carnal minds and fallen wiſdom; and ſo they cry, Lo here, lo there is Chriſt: <hi>Babel,</hi> confuſed in their Languages, rejecting the Corner-Stone, and builds not upon the Rock of Ages, againſt which the powers of hell and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168482:6"/>
death ſhall not prevail: My people periſh for want of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, ſaith the Lord; they feed on Wind, they eat on that which dyes of it ſelf; they know not the day of my power, and feel not my power; but ſaith the Lord, O profeſſors, where is the power? for my Kingdom ſtands not in words, for then you might all have it; it is eaſie to get words, you have all words, but it ſtands in power; and now ſaith the Lord, I will ſee the power of you all, for mine is the Kingdom and the Power, and my people are a willing people in the day of my power, and they are led by my fpirit and power; and my Worſhip is in the ſpirit and in the truth; my truth is but one in all, my ſpirit, my light, my truth leads into oneneſs ſingleneſs, pureneſs, one heart, one ſoul, one faith, one Lord, one baptiſm; my Spirit, my Truth, my Son makes free indeed ſits a top of all the world, over the world, all its pollutions, all its glories, profits, pleaſures, vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; my ſpirit helpeth infirmities, and leads into all truth, into nothing but truth; reproves the world of ſin, of righteouſneſs, and of judgement; the life of my ſpirit conſiſteth not in words, in viſible carnal periſhing things, its not meat, nor drink, but righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and peace, and joy within, that is it which helps with ſighs and groans that cannot be uttered.</p>
            <p>And now all profeſſors and people, with the light of Chriſt, the Candle of the Lord, let all your hearts be ſearched, and the ſecret thoughts and imaginations be brought to light; for that will, and ſhall make you all manifeſt what you are, and where your power is, and with what you worſhip me, ſaith the Lord; for now all vails and coverings ſhall be pulled off from all your faces, and wo to thoſe that are covered with a covering, but not with my ſpirit ſaith the Lord And wo to all you profeſſors and people that ſay you know me, and worſhip me, and yet by your works deny me, ſaith the Lord, ſtriving who ſhall be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt among you, and in your hearts and habits out of my fear, and in the vanities, luſts, profits, pleaſures, honors, places, and worldly preferments, ſeeking to eſtabliſh your ſelves &amp; poſteritie in the midſt of the earth, &amp; build &amp; make great your own houſes, but the houſe of God lyeth waſt, not minding the poor and nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy within you, nor thoſe honeſt ſimple hearted ones who were ever found faithful to that cauſe and truſt committed unto them
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168482:6"/>
vvith you, who freely left all, ventured all, Eſtates, Wives, Children, yea, and their own lives in the high places of the field, for no other end, but that they might enjoy free, true, pure li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to worſhip me, ſaith the Lord, in purity, as I have promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to reveal and make known unto them by my ſpirit of truth, without traditions or inventions of carnal man, and for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving and reſtoring that juſt and good Laws of God written in his, To do unto others as they would be done unto, upon which all the Laws of man ſhould be grounded, &amp; not the wills of men eſtabliſhed for a Law.</p>
            <p>But they ſee and feel by ſad experience otherwiſe; for now many of them are thrown into Holes and Priſons in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in this Nation, and ſome in this County, becauſe they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſubmit unto the wills, and traditions, and inventions of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len man; and now all manner of profaneneſs, as Drunkards, Swearers, Riotous, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> find more favor of many, or moſt of the povvers of this Nation, then my poor innocent harmleſs Saints (ſaith the Lord) who fear me, and tremble at my word, and many of them beaten, reproached, and ſhamefully abuſed by this filthy, ungodly, prophane generation, and ſome Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates ſo called, have juſtified their beaſtly actions, by their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding of them who did it without reproof; yea, and in thee O <hi>Kent</hi> ſome violence (priſonning and whipping) hath been acted againſt them for their true and faithful obedience unto me in what I commanded them; and ſtill the actions of violence and oppreſſion are done upon ſome of them, who cannot in their conſciences ſubmit to the will of unjuſt and unreaſonable men who fear not me.</p>
            <p>And you oh profeſſors in the County, who are intruſted with Power and Authority, have you not ſeen and known theſe things, and yet kept ſilence; to my Witneſs within you do I ſpeak, which vvill not lye; you have not remembred the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of my innocent <hi>Joſephs;</hi> and now ſaith the Lord, I will ariſe and plead their cauſe my ſelf, in truth, in righteouſneſs, and in judgement, and I will ſupport them with my ſtrength to ſuffer and bear patiently, and vvill clear up their innnocency, and they ſhall give me the glory; but ſhame and confuſion ſhall haſten upon the top of mine and their Enemies for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:168482:7"/>And as in this vvhole Nation, ſo theſe iniquities are found in thee O <hi>Kent,</hi> which is none of thy leaſt abominations in my ſight, ſaith the Lord; The Heads in thee judge for rewards, and the Prieſts in thee teach for hire, and thy Prophets propheſie for money, and yet thou vvilt lean upon me, ſaith the Lord; and thou haſt given me many vvords and promiſes of reforming theſe things, ſaith the Lord; but thou art deceitful; and thou haſt engaged and vowed in my preſence againſt them, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Popiſh Innovations, but thou haſt not kept them, and as yet I have nothing but thy back, I have not thy face; and yet thou talkeſt of me, and ſaiſt, Is not the Lord amongſt us? though all theſe abominations are found in thee: But for theſe things, as with the Nations, ſo will I plead with thee oh <hi>Kent,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thou repent and turn unto me ſaith the Lord, and forſake theſe thy abominable things in my ſight, ye profeſſors, Prieſts, and people, I will come upon thee on a day before thou art a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, and will reward thee double for all thy iniquities, ſaith the Lord; and as thou haſt drunk deep of the Cup of thy Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo thou ſhalt drink deep of the Cup of my Indignation; and if theſe things thou departeſt not from, and turn unto me with all thy heart, oh people unworthy to be beloved; if thou waſt as <hi>Zion,</hi> for theſe things thou ſhouldſt be plowed as a field; and as Jeruſalem, thou ſhalt be laid on heaps; and though the Mountains of thy Houſe be as the High Places, yet thou ſhalt be laid as a Forreſt before me ſaith the Lord.</p>
            <p>But if thou wilt repent and turn unto me ſaith the Lord, unfeignedly with all thy heart, and hear and obey the voice of my ſervants and Miniſters which I have ſent unto thee, and now of late raiſed up in thee gifted with my own ſpirit, in the light of my own Son, who is the true light which enlightneth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man that cometh into the world; and turn away from all thy falſe Hirelings and Teachers, which run and I never ſent them, and have not received their vvords from my mouth, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit not the people at all, but declare their own dreams, and tell of viſions and imaginations of their own hearts, which I never ſpake to them, which reaches not my Witneſs, and burdens my ſeed; which ſeed cryes for the bread of life, living bread, living water from my living Fountain of light and life.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:168482:7"/>Then, oh then ſhal it go wel with thee oh Nation! oh Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty! oh people! ſaith the Lord; and I will be your Teacher, I will be your Paſtor, your Father, and you ſhall be my children; and I will be with you, and bleſs and multiply you, and you ſhall know your Teacher in the midſt of you, and your Bread and Waters ſhal never fail you, no want in your dwellings, and peace ſhall flow in as a River, and plenty as a Flood unto you; and I will be a Wall about you, and for good will watch over you; and I will bring forth my living Witneſſes in you, which ſhall declare and make known my everlaſting Goſpel with life and power unto you, and ſhall freely and boldly declare it in the midſt of you, who ſhall not flatter nor ſpare mine Enemies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, who ſhall not ſeek themſelves, but my glory and Name to be exalted in the midſt of you; who ſhall not preach for hire, nor ſeek gain from any quarter of you, but ſhal preach the Goſpel, and live of the Goſpel with you; and I will be with them, to preſerve and keep them as the apple of mine eye in the midſt of you. And you Powers, touch not mine anointed, nor do my Prophets no harm, I warn and charge you ſaith the Lord; for vengeance is mine, &amp; I wil repay it unto you. And you O people, priſe the Lords love now tendred unto you, and know this day of your viſitation before it be hid from you, and that day of his fierce wrath over take you, in the which you will ſay, We have no pleaſure in it; and then you ſhall remember that you were warned in your life time by him who is a lover of all your ſouls, and known unto many of you by the Name of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Howſeyor.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:168482:8"/>
            <head>Oh City and Town, you are weighed, and found too light: Repent, repent.</head>
            <p>AND thou City of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and Town of <hi>Maidſtone,</hi> to you the Inhabitants and people thereof are theſe lines gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven forth and vvritten: You are great, and greatly encreaſed in riches and ſtrength of this World, and you ſet as Ladyes and Queens in the County, and in your hearts (as your actions de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare) ſay you have need of nothing; but vvith the light of Chriſt you might ſee, and are ſeen, that you are poor, miſerable, blind and naked; you have gotten names and diſtinctions of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, and in vvords vvith your tongues ſpoken, you ſay (every party of you) vve vvorſhip the true God; and ſo that which is but one, and vvithout ſeam or diviſion, you would rent and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide among you, and in your ſenſual and fallen vviſdoms you vvould imagine a vvorſhip to me, and according to the number of your Tribes ſo you make you Gods to vvorſhip: Oh fooliſh people! ſaith the Lord God, and will not come down to my Witneſs, my Spirit of Truth, the Light, my Son, with vvhom I am vvel pleaſed, and with all thoſe who have learned of him to vvorſhip me in the Spirit and the Truth; and ſo you not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him and his vvitneſs within you, know not me, nor cannot come to me; for no man knovveth me but him to whom my Son (the true light, vvhich enlightneth every one that cometh into the vvorld) draweth and revealeth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. 27. And not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving him, nor feeling him within to guide, you have gotten a Profeſſion, but vvant the poſſeſſion; and forms you have, but vvant the povver; the Saints vvords and practiſes to talk of you have gotten, and imitations you have gotten, but vvant the life vvhich they vvere in, and feel not the life that they felt, vvho in the life had dominion over their vvills, their luſts, their pride, their paſſion, their envie, their hatred, ſtrife and debate, wrath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, maliciouſneſs, idle vvords, idle talking, and vain jeſting, vvhiſpering and backiting, they vvere in the life, and vvitneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168482:8"/>
redemption from the vvorld and its vain converſations, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, pleaſures, vanities, luſts pollutions, faſhions, words, wayes, worſhips, and empty traditions, and beggarly Elements and Rudiments, that periſh in the uſing: They vvitneſſed the life, that grace that taught them to deny all ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, and that led them to live ſoberly, holy in all manner of converſation in this preſent evil World.</p>
            <p>Now then try your ſelves you profeſſors in theſe Tovvns, all of you, ſee if this life you vvitneſs, and by it ſet over the vvorld and your luſts, otherwiſe all your profeſſions are vain; and to the light in all your conſciences come down, that wil let you ſee where you are, and vvitneſs for God againſt you all, that you are far from the life and povver of God, and not like the Saints that gave forth Scriptures; and ſo vvith the light of Chriſt you are ſeen, and by the children of Light denied.</p>
            <p>And you who call your ſelves <hi>Independents</hi> in theſe Towns, you are become many of you more proud, and vain, and light in your Attires, and more envious and malicious in your pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes againſt the children of light then that people of the Nation and Towns that you ſay you are ſeperated from; and though you talk of Liberty, &amp; Freedom, and Church Priviledges as you call them; and though you once cryed out againſt your forefathers, the Biſhops and Presbyters, when you were ſervants and in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage under them, yet now your ſelves being become Maſters, your hands are as heavie as their loyns, and that many of the ſervants of the Lord have felt in this Nation, and ſome in this County in your Towns.</p>
            <p>And though you are as Siſters together, as <hi>Samaria</hi> the elder, &amp; <hi>Sodom</hi> the yonger, yet thou art become worſe then thy elder Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Samaria,</hi> and art become more brutiſh and beaſtly then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Heathen; thou art grown haughty and high minded, r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſting truth with impudencie, refuſing to hear the counſel of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lord from the mouth of his Meſſengers, which would deal pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nly and faithfully with thee, and ſhew thee all thy abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; but thou muſt have them to teach thee that will ſpeak pleaſing things unto thee, and daub thee with untempered mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and healthy wounds ſlightly, and lay Pillows under thee that thou mayeſtly down ſoftly; but wo to you that live at eaſe,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168482:9"/>
you careleſs Daughters that are at eaſe, and to you Paſtors that are at eaſe, and thou O <hi>Babylon</hi> that art at eaſe, thy Inhabitants will I diſquiet ſaith the Lord, <hi>Moah</hi> hath been at eaſe from his youth; wo to the Heathen that are at eaſe; wo, wo to all you that have ſlain the Witneſſe in the ſtreets, &amp; now grow merry on the earth over the Witneſs; the Lord God of Power will raiſe to life his own Witneſs, his true &amp; faithful Witneſs; <hi>Rev</hi> 1.5. Jeſus Chriſt the Light of the world, he is the faithful Witneſs, and by him all ſhall be judged; he will call forth his own Witneſs in you all, and he will be a ſwift witneſs againſt all that do wickedly, againſt all you ſcorners, haters, deſpiſers of them that fear the Lord; you proud and lofty ones, I warn you all betimes, Come down to the Witneſs of God in you all which will tell you that you ſhould not live in your pride, nor luſts, nor pleaſures, for he that is there, is dead while he lives. So I warn you all again, Take heed you go not from it, but hear its voice; do nothing which he reproves &amp; teſtifies againſt, &amp; when any from the Lord ſpeaks to the raiſing of him in you, be ſtil, let the Witneſs ſtand on his feet, hear his teſtimony I warn you all that the enemy of your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal peace may he diſcovered, and with the breath of his mouth, and brightneſs of his coming utterly deſtroyed, that ſo the life of the Juſt by you may be witneſſed, which is by faith in the Son of God, the Light; it's not in words and ſhadows, as Clouds without rain; but in life and power, with joy and peace in the Holy Ghoſt. So all of you while you have time priſe it, and mind the light of Chriſt in you all, by it to be ordered in every thing, that your lives may preach forth holineſs in all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of converſation; which is the deſire of him who is a friend to truth, and to ſome of you known by the name of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:168482:9"/>
            <head>To thoſe called Magiſtrates and Juſtices in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> a warning that you ſhed no innocent blood.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>To</hi> Michael Leuſey, <hi>High Sheriff of the County, with thoſe in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Power and Authority.</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis is the Word of the Lord God of life and power to you all, who is over you all, bleſſed for evermore: I am he by whom Kings reign, and Governors make Decrees, who ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth all hearts, and knoweth all ſecrets, and will do righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and reward all according to their works and doings; I am he that reſpecteth no mans perſon, but every where thoſe that fear me, and work righteouſneſs, ſhall be accepted.</p>
            <p>Yea, I am he ſaith the Lord, who hath preſerved and defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many of you when the Sword was drawn, and drunk much blood in your Land, and in your County; and you have ſeen my ſtrong Arm, which is mighty to ſave and deliver in the day of battel, and have brought to nought the plottings and conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of mine and your Enemies to this day.</p>
            <p>And you are preſerved to this day, and intruſted with my power, and in places of Government in this County, not to pleaſe your ſelvs, not to ſeek your ſelvs, but in all things him who hath kept, and preſerved, and intruſted you in his ſervice, and for me (ſaith the Lord) to govern, and on me to wait, pure wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and counſel to receive, all things to do and order, to the praiſe and glory of my Name, who hath the whole power, and there is no other with me, nor like unto me, ſaith the Lord, who kills and makes alive; throweth down one, and exalteth whom I pleaſe.</p>
            <p>Therefore O ye Powers of the earth, fear before me conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuallie, and tremble at my word, which is a ſword and a fire that will devour all bryars and thorns, yea all that ſtand againſt it, but it is good to all that walk uprightly; yea, my Word is nigh unto you, I have placed a meaſure of my ſelf, my eternal Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168482:10"/>
that wil not conſent to any evil; in your conſciences it is, that vvil, that ſhall accuſe you when you do evil, and excuſe you when you are righteouſly, juſtly, ſingly, uprightly: And this my word is light in you all, and doth make manifeſt all your deeds of darkneſs, and doth not ſpare, but reproveth plainly, it's that which ſearcheth the heart, and tryeth the reins, and knoweth all your thoughts; I am he, ſaith the Lord, ſtand in awe before me.</p>
            <p>And this is my word now to you all, that you mind my eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Witneſs placed in the midſt of you, and that to it you keep at all times, in all places, and by it to be ordered in all you do, in every thing committed to your truſt, that you never depart from it, but in its power you alwaies ſtand, that the unruly and diſobedient by it in you all may be brought low, and your own wils denyed in every thing; that you begin at home to lay the yoke upon the unruly, and the ſword upon the tranſgreſſor, to cut him out out of the Land, that it may be cleanſed from the evil doer in your own particular, that ſo my wil which is pure being done in you, and by you, and my Law which is undefiled being written in your hearts, and you all in my fear abide, wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the light of Chriſt which hath ſhined into your own ſouls, and ſhewn you the Enemy there, and paſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>udgement on him there, you in that abiding wil be compleatly furniſhed with my wiſdom, ſaith the Lord, to govern and rule over men in righteouſneſs, and ſo you wil all become a terror to the evil doer at home, abroad, at all times, in all ſeaſons, but a praiſe and incouragement to them that do wel; and then the end for which I the Lord have ordained Magiſtrates to rule, wil by you in your places be truly accompliſhed; and then ſhall the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in you rejoice, and that wicked ſhal be brought to ſhame; then ſhal you be to the juſt as the rain to the Land new ſown; then ſhal the righteous in the County praiſe my Name for you, and I wil eſtabliſh you in peace, who makes peace, and none can make war, and exalt you above all your enemies at home and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad; but if from my teachings, my Witneſs in the midſt of you ye turn, and his voice wil not hear and obey, then my wil by you wil be denied, your ovvn vvils vvhich are corrupted vvil be done, and then I make vvar, and none can make peace.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:168482:10"/>Novv therefore, O ye men of place and authoritie in that Nation and Countie, I am moved of the Lord to vvarn you all to take heed what you do in all things committed to your pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and truſt, that you therein be found faithful, as the Lords Stevvards, and that none of you go beyond your power, nor yet from the true Povver, the Light of Chriſt in all your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, vvhich vvil ſhevv you, if you keep to it, hovv and vvhen to give <hi>Caeſar</hi> his due, and God his; the conſcience is the Lords, he rules there, that muſt be kept ſingle, holie for him; I vvarn you, Meddle not vvith them that cannot bovv to the vvils of any but God alone; touch not Gods annointed, harm not his innocent Lambs, vvho are as the apple of his eie, vvho dare not do their ovvn vvils, nor pleaſe themſelves, but in all things him, in him all power is; and for him at this day ſtand ſingle, and rather ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the loſs of all their outword injoyments, then to ſin againſt their God by doing any thing contrarie to the Witneſs of God within, and the Scriptures recorded without; I am free to tell you it is a good report of you, I mean many of you in thi Countie, vvho have not appeared forward as yet to ſhed inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent blood, nor to reſtrain and impriſon the Meſſengers and Miniſters of Chriſt ſent amongſt us; and if you keep faithful to the Witneſs of God in your conſciences, you vvil never do it whatever it coſt you: And for ſuch of you as are and have been friendlie to truth, and the declarers of it, I can ſafely tel you who are ſingle and upright in what you do, you do, and ſhal know that your rewarder is nigh you, with the Lord our God; and for any who are enemies to us and the truth of our God; their rage ſhal he reſtrain, and we ſhal be enabled with patience and long-ſuffering to bear his vvil and good pleaſure, and in the midſt of all our cruelties to pray our Father to forgive them, they know not what they do.</p>
            <p>Alſo, I deſire and warn you all in Authoritie to take heed that you do not lend your ear to the Prieſts of this Countie that preach for hire, and divine for monie, and if it be not put into their mouths they prepare war againſt their Neighbor; for that generation the Scriptures of truth declare to be bloodie, they ſmote the Prophets, they cried, crucifie the Son of God, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168482:11"/>
ſaid he was worthy to die; that generation in theſe daies are lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle behind them, their Fathers eat the Grapes, and their teeth are on edge; they go ſo faſt as they durſt, and wait for further pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: Oh ye Power of the Earth! take heed what ye do in deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the innocent ſervants of God into their hands; for the beſt of their mercies and cruelties, as many priſons in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if not ſome in this Countie, wil witneſs, where many of the ſervants of the Lord have laine many months, becauſe they cannot in their conſciences pay them (as they call it) tithes, that idle, antichriſtian, beggarlie Rudiment, which none of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt do, or durſt own or compel the Saints unto, but did rather labour with their hands then make their Goſpel chargeable to any, who ſaid they had freely received, and did freelie give; and ſo the Miniſters of Chriſt do now: <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.14. <hi>That God had ordained that they which preach the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel ſhall live of the Goſpel.</hi> Therefore take heed you Powers that you do not go beyond your Power to compel any to pay Tithes to maintain a Goſpel Miniſtrie, when God hath ordained that they were to live of the Goſpel, and ſhould live of the Goſpel and not by the Law; for if you do compel any to that thing, I declare unto you all, you are Enemies to God and his children, and do inaſmuch as in you lieth, cauſe them to diſobey the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God.</p>
            <p>And you may read, that tithes to be paid to the firſt Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, the Levitical Prieſthood, which was after the Order of <hi>Aaron,</hi> not of Chriſt the ſecond Prieſthood, the everlaſting of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering; ſo all that pay tithes, that take tithes, are of the firſt Prieſthood, they denie the ſecond to be come, and the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood to be changed, and the Law changed</p>
            <p>Therefore conſider what you do, all of you, leſt you reſiſt the Povver, God is the Povver, vvhat he hath ordained ſtands vvith povver, and his Goſpel hath in it a povver, and he that reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the povver, reſiſteth the ordinrnce of God: and all ſuch ſhal bring upon themſelves judgement. So all that vvil be out of fear of the Povver, do vvel, and ſo thou ſhalt have praiſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:168482:11"/>
the ſame; but he that doth evil is under the povver, and the Svvord is not placed there for naught; but vvil take vengeance on them that do evill vvithout reſpect of perſons.</p>
            <p>Let none deceive you vvith their vain vvords, and flattering ſpeeches, vvho ſeeks not the good of your ſouls but their own bellies, and now do the ſame things the Prelates and Prieſts did before them, by vvhoſe means much innocent blood hath been ſhed in theſe Nations.</p>
            <p>So to that of God in all your conſciences I have and do ſpeak, which is the witneſs for God, and wil not deal deceitfully with you, but wil ſpeak the truth, if you wil hear it, to all of you; and if anie now ſhal refuſe to hear its voice, and wil not receive its teſtimonie which is truth, there wil come a day in which the Lord wil have his everlaſting witneſs come forth, and if that condemn, he is greater; ſo in the mouth of two Witneſſes all ſhal be confirmed; therefore now hear and be warned eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one of you, and do nothing in your own wils but wait in the pure light of Chriſt, and by it be directed and ordered at all times in all things; quench not its motions, ſtay not behinde it; neither go before it, for if you do you ſhal be judged and condemned by it: And bleſſed are all thoſe that love the light and walk in the Light, and believe in the Light, and become o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient children to the Light, ſuch have their part in the firſt Reſurrection, and over them the ſecond death ſhal have no power.</p>
            <p>And to ſo manie as receive him, and believe in him, and obey him, of him they receive power, and are become the ſons of God.</p>
            <p>But all that denie him before men, he wil denie them before his Father which is in heaven.</p>
            <p>So in love to all your ſouls, which are more worth then all the world, then all your honor, then all your riches, I warn you all to minde the light of Chriſt in you all, the witneſs for God, by it to be ordered in everie thing, word, and work, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, become children of it, and if you walk in the light, as he is in the light, you have fellowſhip with him and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168482:12"/>
and by his blood you are all purged from all ſin; but if you denie the light of Chriſt, and wil not obey its teachings, by it you ſhall be eternally condemned, and then wo and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation ſhall be your portion for ever.</p>
            <p>This is the Word of the Lord God unto you all, whether you heare or forbeare, declared and given forth by him who is a friend to all your ſouls, and ſeeks the redemption of the ſeed out of bondage; and am known to manie of you by the name of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Howſeyor.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
